Guide to the Women in the Fire Service Records WAG.320
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Women in the Fire Service Records
1980-2021
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Women in the Fire Service (Organization)
Willing, Linda F.
Berkman, Brenda
WAG.320
20.3 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons, 2 flat boxes and 2 half manuscript boxes.
6 videocassettes (betacamsp)
2 websites in two archived websites.
Women in the Fire Service (WFS) was formed by firefighters Linda Willing and Terese Floren in the early 1980s. It functioned as a network and advocacy organization for women firefighters. The collection consists of administrative files, correspondence, legal files, surveys, and conference materials related to Women in the Fire Service. The records document the efforts by WFS to fight discrimination again women in the fire services by organizing and supporting women firefighters. Particularly valuable are the files on individual women firefighters.
Separated Materials
A complete run of WFS newsletters were separated for cataloging, while several dozen VHS tapes were given to the Non-Print Department.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Brenda Berkman and Linda Willing, 2011, 2012, 2018, and 2023. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2011.059, 2012.086, 2018.136, and 2023.049.
https://www.i-women.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2013 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. In 2015, the website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2019, https://www.i-women.org/ redirected to https://www.womeninfire.org/ and was added to the web archives. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.005.
Historical Note
Women in the Fire Service (WFS) was formed by firefighters Linda Willing and Terese Floren in the early 1980s. It functioned as a network and advocacy organization for women firefighters.
The beginning of the organization was the two women's decision in 1981 to publish a directory of women members of the fire service and a newsletter. Although the first issue of both publications was produced in 1982, WFS was not legally established until the following year.
Throughout its history, WFS fought discrimination and sexual harassment against women in the fire services. The scope of the challenge can been seen from the results of their 1995 survey. Of the 551 women who responded, 88% reported having suffered some sexual harassment during their careers. 69% reported that they were currently subject to sexual harassment.
WFS continued operating until September 2007, when it merged with the Women Chief Fire Officers (WCFO) to form the International Association of Women in Fire and Emergency Services (iWomen).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of administrative files, correspondence, legal files, surveys, and conference materials related to Women in the Fire Service. The records document the efforts by WFS to fight discrimination again women in the fire services by organizing and supporting women firefighters. Particularly valuable are the files on individual women firefighters.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Original order is unknown.
Appraisal
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Sex discrimination against women -- United States.; Women fire fighters -- United States.; Women -- Employment -- United States.; Web sites.; Berkman, Brenda; Willing, Linda F.; Women in the Fire Service (Organization); Willing, Linda F.; Berkman, Brenda
- Inventory
  - Topical Files, early 1990s-early 2000s (Box 1)
  - Speaking/Training/Projects, mid 1980s-early 2000s (Box 1)
  - State and Local Departments: Studies, etc., early 1990s-mid 1990s (Box 1)
  - Other Women Firefighters and Firefighter Organizations, late 1980s-early 2000s (Box 1)
  - United States Fire Administration, 1992 (Box 1)
  - International Women Firefighters and Firefighter Organizations, early 1990s-mid 2000s (Box 1)
  - Publications, early 1980s-mid 2000s (Box 2)
  - Legal Files, mid 1980s-mid 2000s (Box 2)
  - Files on Women Firefighters: A (Box 2)
  - Files on Individual Women Firefighters: B-O (Box 3)
  - Files on Individual Women Firefighters: P-Z (Box 4)
  - Sexual Harassment and Discriminatory Policies, early 1980s-mid 2000s (Box 4)
  - Sexual Harassment and Discriminatory Policies, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, early 1980s (Box 5)
  - Newsletter Proofs, 1990s (Box 5)
  - Fire Service Directories and Other Publications, early 1980s-early 1990s (Box 5)
  - Linda Willing, early 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 6)
  - Surveys, 1980-1995 (Box 6)
  - Conference Materials, 1980s (Box 6)
  - Conference: Oakland, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Phoenix, 2006 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Maryland, 2005 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Miami, 2004 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Denver, 2003 (Box 7)
  - Conference: San Diego, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Cobb Co. Georgia, 2001 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Madison, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Los Angeles, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Conference: Los Angeles, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Conference: San Diego, 1998 (Box 8)
  - Conference: Austin, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Conference: Madison, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Conference: Fairfax, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Conference: Fairfax, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Conference: Madison, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Conference: Rockford, IL, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Conference: San Diego, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Conference: Ashville, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Conference: Boulder, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Conference Materials, early 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 9)
  - Subject Files, mid 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 9)
  - Conference: Seattle, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Legal Files, early 1980s-early 2000s (Box 10)
  - Academic Studies, early 1980s-late 1990s (Box 10)
  - Reports, late 1980s-mid 1990s (Box 10)
  - Administrative Files, early 1990s-early 2000s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, early 1980s-early 2000s (Box 11)
  - Audiotapes (Box 11)
  - Oversized Material: Posters, plaque, and quilt, undated (Box 12)
  - Inactive Members Correspondence: A-P (Box 13)
  - Inactive Members Correspondence: R-Z (Box 14)
  - Inactive Members Correspondence (1991): A-Z (Box 14)
  - Surveys, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Surveys, 1995 (Box 16)
  - Interviews on VHS Tapes, Mini DVs, and CDs (inventory in box), 1990s-2000s, undated (Box 17)
  - Oral History Handbook, transcripts, 2007 (Box 17)
  - Women in the Services plaque, undated (Box 18)
  - Audiovisual Recordings of Firefighter Interviews, 1999 (Box 19)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Contains 6 betacam tapes.
  - Banner (Box 20)
  - Brochure, 2021 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "Women Firefighters' Strategies for Advancement in the Fire Service" by Barbara R. Russo, 2013 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - California Women in the Fire Service Newsletters, 1989-1995 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
- Archived Websites, November 2013-ongoing; 2 websites in two archived websites.
  Scope and Content Note
  Women in Fire (formerly known as International Association of Women in Fire & Emergency Service [iWomen]) is descended from Women in the Fire Service (WFS), Inc., which began in 1982. In September 2007, WFS merged with the Women Chief Fire Officers (WCFO) to form the iWomen. Women in Fire supports, mentors, and educates current and future women in the fire and emergency services. The website includes a photo gallery, news and job postings, position statements, reports, guidelines and procedures, and other information about the association.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of i-women.org in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.